hey what's up guys My Name Is AO and
welcome back to my C++ Series so today
let's get our tools set up so in order
for us to write programs in C++ we need
to have a computer and then a set of
tools that will let us build C++
programs these tools of course are going
to depend on which operating system
you're using so this video is going to
cover windows but if you're using Mac or
Linux then just click on the screen and
you'll be taken to those videos cuz I
made them as well all right so Windows
excellent choice because Windows is the
most widely used operating system in the
games industry now to write C++ code all
you really need is just some kind of
text editor like notepad for example
will do fine however once you've written
that code in C++ as a text file we need
to take that and pass it through a
compiler to generate some kind of
executable binary so that we can run our
program so what we need at the very
minimum is a compiler that will take
that text that we've written and convert
it into a program however we can do a
lot better than that writing C++ isn't
the easiest task and if you're using
something like notepad it's really just
going to not help you at all so what you
can do instead is actually get a
development environment something called
an integrated development environment
this is basically a set of tools that
helps you write and debug your code in
our case since we're on Windows we're
going to be using something called
Microsoft Visual Studio which is pretty
much the best ID out there now don't get
me wrong it's far from perfect but it is
the best thing that we've got I've used
a lot of different idas and it's by far
my favorite Visual Studio has plugins
that will help you target pretty much
any platform like P PC Mobile consoles
everything which is why it's the most
popular IDE in the games industry so
without further Ado let's go ahead and
install that all right so here we have
Windows 10 doesn't really matter what
version of Windows you're using we're
going to basically head on over to
visual studio.com link will be in the
description if you don't want to type
that out we're going to click on
download visual studio and we're going
to get community 2017 now Visual Studio
Community is absolutely free and once
it's downloaded we're going to want to
install that and installing Visual
Studio will take a significant amount of
time so you might want to come back now
this is Visual Studio 2017 which is
quite a bit better than 2015 it's a lot
faster and it has some pretty nice new
features and it's also going to be the
ID that we use for the entirety of this
series now while this is happening I
want to quickly mention that there is
actually a plugin called visual assist
which I use just all the time I haven't
used Visual Studio without visual assist
for probably the last 2 years it's
amazing now it does cost money it's like
I think it's
$99 yeah $99 for personal license but if
you do write a lot of code in Visual
Studio I highly recommend it it's
amazing it basically just gives you a
lot of features the visual studio is
missing and I mean they're not paying me
to say that I genuinely love visual
assist so yeah all right so visual
studio taking its time as usual now in
terms of what components we want Visual
Studio 2017 has this brand new installer
that has like a lot of things way more
than 2015 um the gist of what we really
want is the easiest way to go through
this is just to pick desktop development
with C++ that includes pretty much
everything you need we don't need un
universal windows platform development
that's actually that's something called
wwp which is actually something entirely
different uh net is something that you
probably want to install if you're using
stuff like C I'm actually going to be
using that so I might install that but
all you really need to follow along with
this series is going to be C++ um
desktop development with C++ and you
don't actually need everything that's
included in here like this has stuff
like um sa for cake and ATL support and
we don't really need that but uh
the easiest way again to install this is
just to click on desktop development
with C++ and be done with it so we'll
hit install and now it's going to start
downloading and installing everything we
need so this will really take a while
all right so now that Visual Studio is
installed let's go ahead and launch it
you can either quick click launch or you
can you know get rid of this and then
click launch it's up to you so visual
studio open you're going to want to
probably log in with your account this
is just any Microsoft account okay and
here we see this start page so things
that I like to get done out of the box I
like to customize my settings and stuff
like that for example under Tools
options you can go and change to dark
mode for example I quite like dark mode
there's a color theme you can just go
ahead and change that to dark you can
see it's actually already loaded my
settings just from the cloud and
everything now I've set up visual studio
the way that I like to use it including
like the syntax highlighting theme and
everything like that if you guys want to
use the same settings as me you can just
go ahead and go to the ch.com for vs the
link will be in the in the description
and you'll download this vs settings
file once you've downloaded that file
you're going to want to put it into
documents Visual Studio 2017 settings
and then just paste it in there and then
back in Visual Studio you can go tools
Import and Export settings import
selected environment settings hit next
just import new settings don't worry
about exporting your old one since it's
a fresh install uh chov vs is the one
you want to use um and then of course
set up any setting well all of them is
really what you want um under general
settings it hasn't done everything but I
mean the default options are usually
pretty good just hit finish and
everything uh should work now if you
don't have visual assist installed you
you might get some warnings I haven't
actually installed visual assist I might
install it and then you know rerun this
thing but anyway if you hit close
everything should be set up the way that
I like it now so let's just make sure
everything works by creating a new
solution uh you can actually click on um
there's a bunch of pro templates I'm not
sure visual 2 2017 has changed a bit but
basic we're just going to go file new
project uh and then under visual C++
under General there'll be a template
called empty project we're going to
select that uh put it anywhere you like
I recommend that you put it into C Dev
I've actually made a folder for it
inside cev and then CPP series The
reason I don't like having it here
because first of all this path is huge
second of all you'll see in my case this
path actually has a space in it which
will cause problems with some some
plugins for example some components of
nvidia's Android plugins for visual
studio actually just won't work if your
path has a space in it so that's already
bad news also this puts it in your users
directory which isn't really necessary
so I like to have it just literally cev
and then whatever my project is so in
this case CPP series that's actually
where I'm going to put it um you can
give it a name I'll call this hello
world we literally just going to write a
little hello world application that will
print hello world to the console and
test out our entire toolchain now you'll
see there's also something called a
solution name Visual Studio has
Solutions and projects think of a
solution as like a group of projects
that are related to each other they can
be various project types basically a
solution is like your workbench and then
each project is essentially just a group
of files which compile into some kind of
Target binary whether that be a library
or an actual executable so that looks
pretty good to me I'm just going to hit
okay and we should be taken into our
project all right now I like to have my
solution Explorer on the left all we're
going to do for now is right click on
source files hit add new item under C++
file we're just going to call it
main.cpp hit add then I'm going to type
hash include IO stream in
Main and then I'm going to do s stdc out
hello
world STD
endline I'm going to type in
stdcin.get and then I'm going to right
click on my project and hit build build
we'll have our output window show up and
make sure that everything succeeded
there you can see that it's generated a
hello world.exe file which is an
executable binary for Windows and now
you can run it either by going to this
directory in fact let's let's take a
look at this directory hey look hello
world.exe so we can either run it by
just double clicking it here and you can
see there's our application hello world
and if we press any key then well if we
press enter it will terminate or we can
run it by just clicking on local Windows
debugger which will actually build and
run it so there you go and we're
actually debugging the code right now so
that's it we've got our application
running we've written our first
application in C++ and we' verified that
our tools work properly if you guys had
any problems with this or something
didn't go according to plan leave a
comment below and we'll see if we can
help you out all right sweet so visual
studio is installed and we're ready to
go and learn some C++ over the next few
videos we're going to learn how C++
actually works knowing how C++ actually
works is pretty much the biggest key to
writing C++ code properly make sure you
follow me on Twitter and Instagram and
if you really like this series you can
support it on patreon but until next
time goodbye vom